so I'd like to read from some talks on
margin cha recorded Hawks
transpose this one is caused about being
careful and it could be found
the Buddha taught to see the body in the
body what does it mean we are all
familiar with the parts of the body such
as hair nails teeth and skinny so how do
we see the body in the body if we
recognize all these things as being
impermanent unsatisfactory and not self
that is what is called seeing the body
and the body then it isn't necessary to
go into detail and meditate on separate
on the separate part it's like having
fruit in the basket if we have already
counted the pieces of fruit then we know
what's there when we need to we can pick
up the baskets to take it away and all
the pieces come with it we know the
fruits are all there so we don't have to
counter it again having metic meditated
on the 52 parts of the body and
recognized them as something not stable
or permanent we no longer need to worry
ourselves separating them like this and
meditating in such detail just that with
the basket of fruit we don't have to
dump all the food out and counter the
game in the end we do carry the basket
along to our destination walking
mindfully and heavy
taking care not to stumble fall
when we see the body in the body which
means we see the dummer in the body
knowing our own and others bodies as
impermanent phenomena then we don't need
detailed explanations sitting here you
have mind constantly
knowing things as they are meditation
then becomes quite something it's the
same if we meditate on the word Buddha
if we understand what Buddha really is
and we don't need to repeat the word
widow it means having full knowledge and
firm awareness
this is meditation
having the inner sensitivity that is
always aware of right and wrong is
called Buddha it's not necessary to be
continually repeating Buddha
you've counted the fruit in your basket
every time you sit down
you don't have to go to the trouble of
spelling out the fruit and can't be
counting it again hmm you can leave it
in the box but someone was mistaken
attachment will keep counting he'll stop
under III spin it out and count will put
it back in the basket then you'll walk
onto the next public place and do it
again but he's just counting the same
food this is craving itself he's afraid that
this is craving itself he's afraid that
if he doesn't count every some mistake
we are afraid that you don't keep saying
Buddha will be mistaken how are we
mistaken it's only the person who
doesn't know how much fruit there is who
needs to count once you know you can
take it easy and just leave it in the
basket when you're sitting you just sit
when you're lying down you just lie down
because your fruit is all day with you
or the same go for another you should
see all the forms of craving which cause
us to have desires but talking about
desire can be confused some people get
the idea that any kind of desire such as
desire for food and for material
requisites for life is crazy but we can
have this kind of desire in an ordinary
and natural way when you're hungry and
desire food you can take a meal and be
done with it
that's quite ordinary this is the desire
that's within boundaries it doesn't have
real effects this kind of desire human
sensuality if its sensuality then it
becomes something more than desire they
will be craving for more things to
consume seeking up tales of speaking
enjoyments in why you can't watch it you
could just read that as an inspirational
story oh yeah just be mindful and what not
oh yeah just be mindful and what not
which is usually how I would hear people
talk about I didn't cha but you could be
quite strict about things he's saying
and you could see so so what is in
common what is in common too to not
constantly counting the parts of your
body not constantly reviewing your body
what is in common to not constantly
repeating to the Buddha Buddha or
touching touching moving moving sitting
sitting hair nails skin what is in
common to that the common is
establishing your mind upon the context
where Chile first is basket when you
know you have this in your basket you
don't need to keep taking it out and
reviewing it which is usually what most
people's meditation practice is just
keep doing it robotically methodically
and and completely losing the sight of
the context on account of it that's what
I'm talking about the peripheral
awareness is basically becoming aware of the
is basically becoming aware of the
context where but you don't have to keep
reminding yourself what you're doing
because you already know what you're
doing and that's exactly what he's
saying that you already have the basket
you don't need to keep stopping and
chucking the fruit out to count it again
unless your mind is overwhelmed by your
own doubt like a clarity lack of context
craving as he said himself and same with
people do the mantra like yeah you can
bring to your mind Buddha Buddha if that
makes you contemplate the quality of the
Buddha the quality of renunciation the
quality of freedom from suffering and
then discern that context and that's how
you practice Buddha but if you're just
going like like a parrot to yourself
just Budda Budda Budda expecting that
verbal repetition to result in some sort
of samadhi well that's extremely wrong
Somali and same if you result if you're
expecting experience to arise or not
will you just on account of you just
constantly counting your fruit and not
developing knowledge of the basket that
contains all the fruit means that's not
the Somali the Buddha was teaching so
people can not look into this and then
just sort of okay you don't need to look
at anything no count the fruit the first
time review your body as in bringing the
context of a body that's subjected to
sickness ageing and death of a body
that's not in your control of a body
that it's that is subjected to elements
and if reviewing parts of the body will
enable you to discern that context
initially that's fine that's why the
Buddha would have listed those things
but not as a sort of blind methodical
mechanical repetition practice whereby
you don't take responsibility or
determine of the context and then
exactly as I think I describes if you do
it rightly if you discern this context
peripherally it's it's it's very simple
thing to do then to practice you don't
need to keep bringing it up you don't
need to be wondering what do I do next
because there is no next within the mind
established upon the general context the
right context then you would exactly
know this is within the context this is
against the context as in this is
wholesome this is unwholesome
this is unwholesome
and that's all you need to know and
that's exactly the last paragraph you
you mention it yeah people have no sense
of context everything is a problem oh
well that's just craving isn't it you
wanna you want to sit on a nice chair
that's just craving everything is
craving it isn't there is craving that
leads to more craving and there is
craving the leads to the end of craving
so you should crave renunciation you
should crave solitude yeah crave for
those things because they will result in
complete understanding of the nature of
crazy you should crave the ability to be able
you should crave the ability to be able
to withstand the elements the hardships
not like apply the blanket how that
solves craving failing to see that
that's your craving at a time because of
which you don't make any effort towards
abandoning the craving just dismissing
it because it's all craving and that's
origin cherish trust
so those desires are not sensuality
sensuality is clearly unwholesome
intentional and unwholesome yeah you can
keep refining those desires but the
point is to know where the line is and
not just go around mechanically doing
your mantras and the personal techniques
and mechanically denying everything
because everything is craving everything
is impermanent everything is not myself
that's not true the Buddha said things
are on account of which your sense of
self depends basically things that
determine you are impermanent things
that determine you are not are a
suffering that's why you are not your
own he didn't say everything is impermanent
he didn't say everything is impermanent
and everything is suffering everything
is not self no only things that you take
to be yourself need to be seen as
impermanent and what are those things
things rooted in greed aversion delusion
so that's why when people ask me oh is
there any like teacher than you think I
said but I would think it was right that
I would agree with except obviously the
Buddha or jnana Vera I would say most
likely Arjun Shah but not not for some
some some kind of blind devotional
reasons but because see you could read
these passages and you could see
everything we talked about
based on the sutras based in the Vera
he's saying it in his own words
and you can't do that if you haven't
developed understanding of that meaning
of their context it wouldn't occur to
you to say those things
but it's easy to miss Reid because his
instruction it's not it's not very it's
not accurate it's not it's not like
straight to the point it's more generic
so if you have a broader context you can
start understanding it rightly but if
you don't it's gonna be much more easier
to misunderstand I mean even the
specific instructions people will
understand if they have the wrong view
but let alone instructions that are not
as specific which is the way he was
teaching whether maybe it's lost in
translation I don't know but the point
is it's much more open for
misinterpretation as we've seen
firsthand for number of years like
people who live with him still when they
see what he talked what he was teaching
you do that and you can tell that
despite never met as a child but reading
that understanding the sutras you could
see what a broader context is that -
most people remains invisible so here's
another talk from agent cha and this is
a it's a series of question and answers
this one's called monastery of confusion
so teachers feel free to stop me okay
sergeant shot are there any doubts about
practice you need to resolve now so the
questioner when the mind isn't thinking
much that is in sort of a dark and dull
state is this something we should do to
brighten it or should we just sit with
it I didn't shower is this all the time
or when you are sitting in meditation
what exactly is this darkness like is it
lack of wisdom the question when I sit
to meditate I don't get drowsy but my
mind feels dark sort of dense or opaque
I didn't share so you would like to make
your mind wise right change your posture
and do a lot of walking meditation
that's one thing to do you can walk for
three hours at a time until you're ready
tired question I do walking meditation a
couple of hours a day and I usually have
a lot of thinking when I do it
but what really concerns me is the dark
state when I sit should I just try to be
aware of it and let go or is there some
means I should use to counter it I
didn't shower I think maybe your
postures are aren't balanced when you
walk you have a lot of thinking so you
should do a lot of discursive
contemplation then the mind can retreat
from thinking it won't stick there but
never mind
for now increase the time you spend on
the walking meditation focus on that
then if your mind is wandering pull it
out and do some contemplation such as
for example investigation of the body
have you ever done that continuously
rather rather than as an occasional
reflection if you if you if your view of
what meditation is it's mechanical
that's exactly going to be the result
the state to do drowsiness or less
clarity ambiguity mind you for most
people they confuse that for peace they
think that's a peaceful abiding but this
person was asking a question clearly and
understand that it's kind of dark in
he's in dark and that's what your child
said oh you mean unwise you want wisdom
you want clarity you want discernment
what do they do about it did he say
watch your nostrils or just be here now
present holistically or be doing the
mantra no he said you need to think more
think more on the particular topics of
your occasional reflection spend three
hours back and forth reflecting with the
nature of impermanence on your body upon
which you'll experience as a whole sits
up depends on and always was and always
will be so you passed your future your
present is equally determined by the
random presence of the living body
beating heart in your chest a song if
you think that you will be developing
the themes you think about if your theme
is theme of doubt mental states that's
the theme you will be developing and
those states are always within
sensuality confusion around ears which
means all your made efforts those
meditations they don't go towards
clarity they will then automatically be
developing furthering the wrong village
I think I'd trust my polite attention
because it was obvious how misguided
those questions were but you were saying
well I don't think perhaps maybe your
posture or something no it's just
clearly the keys when he sits there is
zero self-awareness it just goes into
the state which most most many people do
you see them on a meditation floor and
the just nothing left and right bobbing
and weaving and whether they describe
that slows the Buddhist Lord meditation
flawed meditation yet the Buddha did
describe that in the certain like they
call themselves meditators but what
happens the Primera to mismanage under
meditation the meditation sensuality the
down not develop faculties because again
the only way to counter that as that
person asked is not through some counter
method its do that active
self-reflection dwelling in the certain
themes if you develop the theme of we
drove up from sensuality which is
fundamentally rooted in the assumption
in your thoughts of sensuality you will
then enter the first John accompanied by
thinking and pondering big surprise not
very kind of blackness darkness darkness
head-nodding no clarity of mindfulness
and thinking and pondering that has
transcended sensuality
what could you dunder stood the roots of
it either the stood the extent of it
either the stood the cessation or you
dwell on that theme you can enter it at
will you just have to remember it which
you would
look continue with these Christians
questioner I feel frustrated because of
my state of mind
I'm not developing Samadhi or wisdom so
for that person he obviously doesn't
know what either Samadhi or wisdom is
but he has some inclination some idea
but most likely for him samadhi pulls
the experience of overwhelming peace
that you're nothing to do it they were
just sitting in what you know striven
then but he's not getting that anymore
either no is he getting any clarity in pageant
no is he getting any clarity in pageant
char handsome when you have this
condition of mind the suffering comes
about because of not knowing there is
doubt as to why the mind is like this
the important principle in meditation is
that whatever occurs don't be in doubt
over it without only adds to the
suffering if the mind is bright and
awake don't doubt that it's a condition
of mind don't doubt that
don't doubt what's in front of it then
learn to see it on its own terms
allow it to arise all those things we
talk about because you get down to
values oh is it this is late but you
can't doubt the dead thing is in front
of it and that's what many people would
still be affecting with their own doubt
so all you need to do is stop habitually
giving in to the doubt in order to see
that doubt is secondary to the reason
phenomenon the state of mind for example
and you can't doubt that sergeant Choi's
pointing out that you need to learn how
to think on those terms on the terms of
the things that have arisen on their own
because even if you doubt that issue the
down will be secondary to those things
so if the mind is Braddock Lee you
recognize it the mind is brightly clear
then you might be doubting about
different things but still the basis is
the basis that's not doubted if the mind
is effectively confusion ambiguity
darkness whatever is that is the basis
because for most people doubt is fueled
by the desire to get rid of the stator
they don't want but the desire to get
the river the state you don't want will
be there because the state that you want
haven't been understood either so there
is no understanding developed in either
of the states wanted stay tuned on lot
of states soon when they had a peaceful
state they have no understanding with
which means they don't recognize in the
reason on its own terms
as a phenomenon which means although
they are not actively doubting it as in
they're not actually trying to get rid
of it
they still susceptible to doubt doubt
has arisen even the doubt exactly you
can recognize it as in the recessional
countdown and you can't doubt that but
that would require you to allow these
things that arise they have a reason to
endure on their own
no just but that's hard thing to do when
your whole notion of practice and
meditation is about doing something or
do this I do this I do this or you know
you don't do anything or I don't do
anything how to do anything that becomes
your doing so you need to unwind their
attitude but not to the point of
dismissing everything and like nothing
is to be done we are already in a bánh
mì you recognize it but then you need to
allow it to endure on its own and keep
your craving to do something on account
of it in check and that's how you get to
the certain thing that's present
presently reason states will move
described as in char continues if it's
dark and dull your mind don't doubt
about that just continue to practice
diligently without getting caught up in
reactions to that state exactly taking
note and being aware of your state of
mind don't have doubts about it it is
just what it is when you entertain
entertain doubts and start grasping at
it and giving it meaning then it's dark
so even if it's no matter what the state
is bright or dark you recognize it on
its own allowing you don't give in to
reaction as he said two words because
that's how the darkness and
really overwhelmed but it doesn't mean
either just ignore everything and just
be at ease with everything because in
order to allow things to do on their own
in order to not keep maintaining your
reactions towards them you need to
develop discernment of the nature but
you will not develop that discernment if
you go completely the other way and
mystify the whole thing whereby just
being here and now in pristine awareness
and whatnot holistically present in in
just the present moment that's that's
completely the other way now first is
you try to get rid of it
of everything this one is you try to
accept everything but you should not be
in a holistically present moment of your
awareness in regard to sensuality
because if you are means you're
welcoming it you're ready tainting it
you're bound by so you want to practice
this sermon but not overdo it no run to
do it
hence the middle way and you recognize
that on the states of the mind whether
it start
whether it's like contentment whether
its sensuality whether it's silver
whatever state it is you recognize it
which means there is has to be some
effort of discernment and contemplation
but if that effort starts to sort of
pick itself up and start doubting itself
that's where you stop now you don't
develop a view that you should always
stop or you should always push forward
and that's why when there's a winner so
how did you cross the shore well I'm not
pushing forward by not pulling backwards
by not standing still
so this is from the same talk monastery
of confusion and the questioner
continues he asks Arve Tucker and
vichara the same I didn't share your
sitting and started suddenly the thought
of someone pops into your head
that's Whittaker the initial thought
then you take the idea of that the
person who start thinking about them in
detail Mitaka is picking it up picking it up
Mitaka is picking it up picking it up
rich ara
is investigating it for example we pick
up the idea of death and then we start
considering it I will die
others will die every living being will
die when they die where will they go
then stop stop and bring it back again
when it gets running like that stop it
again and then go back to mindfulness of
the breath sometimes the discursive
thought will wander off and not come
back so you have to stop it keep at it
until the mind is bright and clear if
you keep keep the discursive thinking
yeah yeah if you practice with Chara
with an object that you are suited to
you may experience the hairs of your
body standing on in tears pouring from
your eyes the state of extreme delight
many different things as joy comes about
thinking I know these I heard this
number of people but I could see that
being quite a common entity you would
even read that but he said quickly you
learn how to think properly you pick up
I don't know say object because it's
already that notion already fused with
the wrong view for many people and you
pick up a theme and then you think about
it you clarify you ponder on it thinking
it ponder so you're not denying it
you're not doing it for the sake of
trying to get rid of it on the contrary
you want to develop the clarity in
regard to that which is present in the
regards to that which is enduring which
has a reason and you can't develop
clarity if your attitude is of trying to
get rid of it so we will be reading this
as clear as it is so proper vitarka
which are and still practice the
meditation for the purpose of shutting off all down
for the purpose of shutting off all down
all thoughts I must stop thinking stop
thinking feeling to see that that's
another thought that they are thinking
at the time you can't stop your thinking
because even the first jhana is not
about stopping the thinking it's about
thinking and pondering away from the
basis of loss aversion and delusion and
then within that you know how to stop
that thinking but even that it's off you
stopping it is just you discerning
mindfulness and imperturbable a movie
better verbal even even even higher than
the domain of thinking and pondering but
you won't get the idea of what that is
until you learn how to think about the
problem as the Buddha said like I became
the simile for the Jannah when a
mountain cow before it sets its foot on
one stone thinking about stepping on the
second one and then falls in between so
that's when people like already have
notions of what cessation of thinking of
pondering is while they even haven't
understood or learn how to do rightly
thinking and pondering in the first
place
and that's what we talk about learning
how to think take a theme dwell on it
self questioning that we always do ask
in this stop don't rush in giving the
answer or this is this is this is this
because that sauce on the level of
psychologizing just ask these questions
because they will force you to endure
the presently arisen situation that you
are questioning but if you provide the
answer that often means or you jumped on
it and I'm going to go for the other
ones and you lost the context you lost
the sides of the peripheral but if you
stay with that questioning you dose
you're not doing it for the sake of self
mystification you want to know but you
don't jump at the answer you allow the
question to endure and that's how
questions get answered on their own
terms not on your frequency of terms and
that's we talk to each other properly
questions continue questioner can this
happen with any kind of thinking the
rapture the joy what is it only in a
state of tranquillity that it happens as
in sure it's when the mind is tranquil
it's not ordinary mental proliferation
yeah you sit with a calm mind and then
the initial thought comes for example I
think that would be sorry don't be
another thing that the person needs to
start discerning first what is the
proliferation what is thinking and
pondering mindful so mindful and mindful
thinking and pondering there is no place
for proliferation absence of that
peripheral awareness in regard to
thinking upon during that's the
proliferation but it's not proliferation
means thinking thus no proliferation
means no thinking yeah you could only
wish is that easy this is for example I
think of my brother who just passed away
well I might think of some other
relatives this is when the mind is
tranquil the tranquility isn't something
certain but for the moment the mind is
Trentham after this initial thought
comes then I go into discursive thought
if it's a line of thinking that's
skillful and wholesome it leads to ease
of mind and happiness and there is
rapture with us with its attendant
experiences this rapture came from the
initial and discursive thinking that
took place in a state of calmness we
don't have to give it name such as first
jhana or second jhana and so forth we
just call it tranquility but it is
nothing mundane about it either
and even thoughts such as his dead
brother we're not necessarily disturbed
at tranquility unless he chose to give
in to it and lost the context lost the
peripheral awareness of his own thinking
lost the sight of it was the theme of it
whichever you want then yeah then he's
affected by
to see Jeff from another tool called
still flowing water
as in charm I've often thought that
tranquility is stillness flowing is
wisdom we practice meditation to calm
the mind and make it still then it can
flow in the beginning we learn what
Stillwater is like and what flowing
water is like after practicing for a
while we see how these two support each
other we have to make the mind calm like
Stillwater then it flows both being
still and flowing there's not easy to
contemplate we can understand that still
water doesn't flow we can understand
that flowing water isn't still but when
we practice we take hold of both of
these the mind of a true practitioner is
like store water it flows if you chase
one eye when there is still this is
flowing there is too much two separate
things and that's why the true
practitioner is the one who discerns
that he sends stillness while flowing
allows flowing while still they're not
on the same footing so it's not a
contradiction in terms of a is being
busy it's a and more a or less a and a
so still this employee it's nothing
other than saying so the Buddha said
arising is manifest for ceasing is
manifest and changing while standing is
medicine so this thing while staying the
same is manifest flowing while being
still is manifest that mystical it's a
third characteristic of as in the most
fundamental characteristics of anything
that has a nature of arising which is
literally everything in your experience
but you're not chasing the contents of
what arises you recognize that basis of
it
so whether things are arising or there
ceasing either way there is persisting while
either way there is persisting while
remaining the same increasing decreasing
either way
the same thing is persisting while
changing and that's the definition of
like it's a we spoke about it before I
don't want to get too technical about it
because then you know what people will
lose the side of this context in
particular when comes the context of
meditation but it's the same thing it's
not like one two three four five in
terms of like a linear flow or something
that means you're already in that flow
now you could see one two three four
five as things flowing as in coming and
going while the context while the peripheral
while the context while the peripheral
context of those things remains
unchanged so what is the most
fundamental context of your experience
in the whole each your current mood as
the Buddha said sorry as I didn't answer
this let's say currently you're tranquil
and you know that's not necessarily
always going to be the case but that's
the case at the time within that
tranquility you have thoughts coming and
going so within this you have this
so we're in the mood that's in the early
it is it is not changing as fast so to
speak that it's there on its own you
have these things coming and going and a
quick rate when you're not losing the
sight of that so you're not chasing
these things coming and going nor are
you mystifying your mood and ignoring
things coming in going you see with this
this is you see with the basis of
inequality I have such and such thoughts
and it's still enduring and if you're
not sure you ask yourself oh it's my
mood and my stuff frankly if the answer
is yes it's still the same thing in
doing it seems is still the same
stillness so if you start this early
stillness rightly it will not be
affected by the flow such as the example
of him being trampled thinking about his
dead brother if he was not established
in a triple even if it's not troubling
if it's any other boon if he were
established properly he would have been
the principle of that development of
that imperturbable as in something
steadier than these particular things so
in in his stillness even the thoughts of
the flowing thoughts of his dead brother
and memories did not overwhelm the mind
did not approved that establishment of
two things simultaneously present
together greater context and things
within the context that's why I keep
using the word context because there's
no context without the content of the
context but the content of the context
is not the context and that's exactly
the context is still in regard to the
flowing content and it gives the meaning
to the flowing content that stillness
but in order to discern that rightly you
need to steal you need to see the domain
of flow and domain of stillness is to
simultaneous things present together but
not the same not completely apartheid
and as we meant that meant for a true
protection that means that's meant for
somebody with the right view
he continues the mind of a true
practition is like still water that
flows yeah a flowing water the sight of
the context no amount of the flow
whatever takes place in in the mind of a
Dharma practitioner is like flowing
water ladies still to say that it is
only flowing is not correct only still
context is you can't conceive context
without the content of it a content of
it has no meaning without a context
saying there is stillness without a flow
it's meaningless oh there is just flow
without stillness it's equally
meaningless if we're wrong but when we
have experience of practice our minds
will be in this condition of flowing
water that is till this is something
we've never seen when we see flowing
water is just flowing along when we see
still water it doesn't flow but within
our minds it will really be like this
like flowing water that is still in our
Dharma practice we have Samadhi or
tranquillity and wisdom mixed together
we have morality meditation of wisdom
then whenever we sit the mind is still
and it flows still flowing water with
meditative stability and wisdom
tranquility and insight it's like this
the dumb ways like this if you have
reached the Dumber then at all times you
will have this experience being tranquil
and having wisdom flower is not
suffering
what is the purpose of Tranquility why
should we have wisdom there are only for
the purpose of freeing ourselves from
suffering nothing else at present we are
suffering living with KUKA not
understanding dukkha and therefore
holding on to it but if the mind is as
I've been speaking about then there will
be many kinds of knowledge one will know
suffering know the cause of suffering
now the cessation of suffering another
way of practice did you reach the end of
that suffering these are the Noble
Truths they will appear of themselves
when there is still flowing water when
the principle of simultaneous dependence
has been understood monotheism policies
with this this is stillness flowing is
when there is flow there is stillness in
regard it's just which way you're gonna
go whether you'll be taking with a grain
of that flow who you will be discerning
against the grain so this again is from
a talk still flowing water I don't
charge some people think that meditation
means to sit on some special way but in
actual fact standing sitting walking and
reclining are all vehicles for
meditation practice you can practice at
all times
Samadhi literally means to firmly
established mind to develop Samadhi you
don't have to go bottling up the mind it
is imperturbable
in regard to sitting walking laying down
so what is the context of the four
postures is the presently enduring mood
not a specific portion specific posture
is secondary to the present body see if
you're mindful the body properly if
you're discerning the theme of the
present body or account of reflection
body parts whatever you take on you will
be then mindful of all the postures
within it
means the mind is established
peripherally in regard to what's
presently actually manifest in front of
him standing walking talking sitting
extending your arm you can't lose your
mindfulness exactly because your
mindfulness is not in the content it's
in regard to the context of the content
the meaning behind it but if you don't
make the effort to discern that theme
that context you are going with the flow
even when you're doing good
meditation practice at the best of your
efforts
it continues some people try to get
peaceful by sitting quietly and having
nothing disturbed them at all but that's
just like being dead the practice of
Samadhi is for developing wisdom and
understanding Samadhi is the firm mind
the one point of mind and which point is
it fixed it's fixed on the point of
balance that's its point but people
practice meditation to try silence their
minds they say I try to sit in
meditation but my mind won't be still
for a minute one instant it flies off
one place the next instant it flies off
somewhere else how can I make it stop
still you don't have to make it stop
that's not the point but it's you being
affected by the moving mind that's the
problem now you don't see that that's
the problem you don't see that it's your
attitude in regard to your own mind a
problem so you blame the mind for it so
you try to stop your thinking you try to
control your environment where nothing
will disturb you because you will not be
able to remain still in regard to the
flowing of your thought so you try to
deny the thought
and he was develop use that that's what
Jonah is a mother
he continues you don't have to make it
stop that's not the point where there is
movement movement is where understanding
can arise people complain it runs off
and I pull it back again then it goes
off again and I pull it back once more
so they just sit there pulling back and
forth like this
you must contemplate in order to find
peace what people usually refer to as
peace is simply the calming of the mind
not the calming of the defilements the
defilements are simply being temporarily
subdued like what I suppose you could
call it but it's not the peace peace
because by denying floats by trying to
not think by strapping everything out
yeah you will not even see what the
problem is so what in the master is
ignoring the problem means there is no
problem he says just like grass covered
by a rock in three or four days you take
the rock off the grass in no long time
it goes goes up again the grass hasn't
really died it was simply being
suppressed it's the same way of sitting
in meditation the mind is calmed but the
defilements are not really calmed
therefore Samadhi is not a sure thing to
find real peace you must develop wisdom
Samadhi is one kind of peace like the
rock covering the grass in a few days
you take the rock away and the grass
because it grows up the game this is
only a temporary peace the peace of
wisdom is like putting the rock down and
not lifting it up just leaving it where
it is the grass cannot possibly grow
again this is real peace the calming of
the farmers the sure peace which results
from wisdom
and wisdom is not a metaphysical
experience transcendental release at the
end of your meditation technique wisdom
is effort to understand brought to
fulfillment understanding understanding
the nature of the reason thing
understanding with the problem
understanding the origin of the problem
the cessation of the tope continues any
case in our practice no matter what
aspect you refer to
you must always begin from the mind do
you know what this mind is what is the
mind like what is it where is it
nobody knows all we know is that we want
to go over here and over there we want
this and we want that we feel good it
would feel bad but the mind itself seems
impossible to know what is the mind the
mind doesn't have form there which
receives impressions both good and bad
we call mind it's like the owner of a
house the owner stays put at home while
visitors come to see him he's the one
who receives the visitors who receives
sense impressions but what is it that
perceives who lets go of sense
impressions that is what we call mind
but people can't see it they think
themselves around in circles what is the
mind what is the brain don't confuse the
issue like this what is it that receives
impressions some impressions it likes
and sums it some it doesn't like who is
that is there one who likes and dislikes
sure there is but you can't see it
there's what we call mind
therefore it is said to begin the
practice by calming the mind put
awareness into the mind if the mind is
away it will be at peace or is this a by
discerning the sign of the mind it's
learning the signs and characteristics
and properties of the mind
unnecessary precondition for the rising
of the right view so how can you develop
the right view how can you know the way
out of suffering if you don't even see
your mind as a thing that's there which
is there but you don't see it and how
can you see it if you never make the
effort to see if all of your efforts are
focused to the content of your mind
dwelling on the contents shutting the
content down being engaged with fully
with the content you'll never step back
to ok the context what's peripheral in
regard to this content and if you never
do that you can never see if the mind is
aware it will be at peace some people
don't go for awareness they just want to
have peace a kind of blanking out yeah
so they never learn anything if we don't
have this one who knows what is there to
base our practice on and see one who
knows I heard many times get mystified
yeah who knows but do you know the one
who knows or are you just mystifying
your experience by ascribing into the
one who knows only whatever you want you
must know it that's why I saw the part
is knowing that you know no just the one
who knows that I took a trust or
whatever mystified experience ahead the
one who knows sure call it that way do
you know him do you fool in the study do
you see his origin do you see it
cessation do you see the way out of it
no you just got out saying he's just
this is just being here like this the
one who knows the pure awareness you
haven't understood any it's all just
literally like a blanket just
keep repeating this to cover everything
yeah because when there is no problem to
be seen there is no problem I kind of
blanking out continues in order to calm
the mind and become aware of the
perceiver of sense impressions we must
observe it follow the one who knows
train the mind until it's pure how pure
should you make it if it's really pure
the mind should be above both good and
evil above even purity it's finished
when you can't suffer when you know
liable to possibility of suffering you
don't have to make that's when the
practice is finished what people call
sitting in meditation is merely a
temporary kind of peace but even in such
a peace there are experiences if an
experience arises there must be someone
who knows it but looks into it
investigates and examines it if the mind
is simply blank then it's that's not so
useful you may see some people who look
very restrained and think they are but
the real peace is not simply the peace
the peaceful mind is not the peace which
says may I be happy never experience any
suffering for this kind of peace
eventually even the attainment of
happiness becomes unsatisfying suffering
results only when you can make your mind
beyond both happiness and suffering will
you find true peace that's the true
peace this is a subject most people
never study they never ready see this
one they never maybe after a questioning
your own views questioning what you
think they see peace is whether that
really is peace while the meditation did
you find helpful well do I have a
reference with truly helpful things
these things up do I know that or I just
go by what makes me feel good
yeah you got a step to start somehow
it's not gonna be perfect but if you
never made the effort to understand it
you're just going to be following
further down the line of the same
imperfection building on top of it so by
questioning your own views you will be
able to see which ones
unless wrong which one I'm less likely
to be wrong
and then be questioning those father's
you get to discern them further and
that's how you abandon the wrong views
not by shutting them out but by fully
penetrating them they get undone so like
all those questions that this person is
asking you could see you can't ask a
question that's not already rooted in
some sort of a view so you recognize
what's my general situation am I free
from suffering or not no means I don't
have the right view means all my
questions they come I'm not right so I
all I can do is not make him make them
as wrong and you make them really really
wrong when you take them for granted at
face value as right questions when you
don't question your questions so he was
asking how they develop peace as well as
if he already knows what peace is but if
you were to know what peace is what
tranquil it is you could be peace and
tranquil you would have the right view
so the question is good in a sense of
well he's at least aiming it's also
tranquility but it's not good because
he's not seeing that his idea of peace
and rapidity cannot be the right one
because if it were right one he wouldn't
be asking the question in the first
place so he would ask what is peace well he
so he would ask what is peace well he
would exactly even more accurately you
recognize I have a notion of peace but
I'm a particular which means that notion
cannot be right so instead of denying
that out of conceit or whatever he
admits it and because of that he can ask
what is peace ask somebody who's he
things he knows in this case he was in
trouble
and if people start thinking like that
then the contradiction that your own
thoughts are carrying in your day life
they practice will become more and more
apparent and you won't be able to
entertain them
you will undo them but if you don't even
question this then you would be having
things saying things like you know that
the one who knows the noble and
completely mystified without any
understanding of the nature of that and
then just use this this mystical kind of
buzzword terminology to sort of glorify
the present moment yeah be in the
present moment but that's not enough you
need to understand the nature of it and
if you start understanding then you
realize as I said many times being in
the present moment is not optional thing
you would always need the present moment
when you think about your past you think
it present and you plan your future you
think you presently so now you pass in
the future are the problem almost
stopped thinking about it
don't plan the future don't think about
the past why not those are just thoughts
so you're blaming your thoughts for your
suffering you're blaming a pass-fail
software or your future which hasn't yet
occurred between your suffering then
cannot be undone by you if it is to
truly in your past because it's done if
you do troll in your future because it
cannot be done but it isn't isn't it
it's in your attitude in regard to your
own thoughts but if you just take things
for granted like knowing your attitude
you know but then don't question even
your own way of questioning just assume
that you already know things rightly
that's a contradiction in terms that you
are not obviously we're all
so you develop stillness amidst the flow
by discerning the context that remains
immovable violet content while it's
content is changing the fundamental like
one of the fundamental context is this
body present here your own body it's a
it's a basis of any any other content of
your experience and if you don't lose
the sight of that context necessary
basis a determination for any experience
you have means you will not be
overwhelmed or affected by any
experience you have on account of your
body and what experience you have no
conquer all experience that's what we
would say all he develops mindfulness to
the body necessary to the to the extent
necessary for final knowledge he
developed the context of a necessary
basis for other things that are
simultaneously present on top of that
basis to the extent necessary for of
mine to be completely free from
ignorance and liability to stop
and necessary basis is what the car is
so he fully relinquish the cards
extinguishing some cars means
occasionally extinguishing of the
ownership of the confusion of the
ignorance of the necessary basis doesn't
remove the necessary basis structurally
the body is still there but removes any
affection that can arise on account of
it that's why for an arahant what's left
is this this body here and all the name
of form externally so no amount of
change in the name from changing the
elements no matter flow will disturb the
fully developed transcended pretty much
extinguished ownership of that
fundamental context cuz if uh if your
experience is rooted necessarily in the
presence of the body here there is
necessary basis your ownership is
redundant it's secondary you are not its
creator you're not its manager either
you can only assume you're the owner you
you are your own because things are
given to you beforehand on their own
when you recognize that experience is
there because the body liable to
experience is simultaneously there there
is no room for the sense of self there
to be that owner and creator of the
experience and that's how it is own not
by denying the experience or denying the
sense of self but we simply realizing
it's impossible to own it because even
your ownership is of the necessary basis
of this random body living here being
present now with the beating heart and
breathing lungs there is no saying if
those things have no same change normal
you say can make a difference so you
realize I won't say is not my own
fundamentally you can't realize that
accidentally because it's completely
against the entire grain of your
experience everything is he going with
that say with that intention of all
intention so you need to keep making
that effort to discern that context
behind any discerning to the extent
necessary then you have fully appointed
any dependence any liability
to the content of that very context
context of the permanent context the
shuffle